Heavy metal exposure can lead to damage
to cell components due to their chemistry.
These metals can engage
in a range of redox
reactions that create reactive oxygen
species and induce
oxidative stress,
leading to damage to macromolecules
including lipids, proteins,
and nucleic acids.
Damage to lipids affects cell membranes,
a structure critical for cell integrity
and both a barrier
and facilitator of movement of materials
in and out of the cell.
Proteins are involved
in numerous functions in the cells
and damage interferes
with protein activity,
including inhibition of enzymes,
inactivation
of proteins,
and change of protein shape and function.
DNA damage can lead to cell death
by apoptosis
or DNA repair, but improper
DNA repair can lead to cancer.